Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
本系列基于并受 希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维教导的启发，
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
旨在探讨两个相互关联领域 之间的进化关系，
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
它们在粗钝与精微层面上 展现了人类的觉知。
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
本系列致力于阐明这种复杂的 互动关系——
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
一方是当代科学对人类神经解剖学 （尤其是自主神经系统）的理解，
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
另一方则是传统瑜伽文献中 所描述的“精微能量系统”。
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最终，本系列试图带领观众 踏上这段探索之旅——
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
透过希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维所传授的冥想， 亲身体验这些内在关联。
The human brain is a universe within us, and understanding its complex geography
“人类大脑是内在的宇宙， 理解其复杂构造，
is a grand adventure of our time, said David Van Essen.
正是我们这个时代最宏伟的探险。” 大卫·范·埃森 (David Van Essen)
Also, the relationship between the brain and spirituality has been studied
此外，大脑与灵性之间的关联 已受到多个不同领域的研究关注。
and we are also on this very fascinating exploration
今天我们很荣幸能与 尊敬的阿希什·普拉丹医生
with our esteemed guest, Dr. Ashish Pradhan,
一同展开这段 极富启发性的探索之旅。
who is a neurologist, a meditation practitioner, and a coach.
他既是一位神经学专家、 也是冥想修行者和教练。
So without any delay, I would like to welcome Dr. Ashish on the program.
事不宜迟， 让我们欢迎阿希什医生。
Welcome, doctor.
欢迎您，医生。
How are you?
近来可好？
I'm very well, thanks, Monika.
我很好，谢谢你，莫妮卡。
Glad to see you again.
很高兴再次见到你。
It's really nice always talking to you.
和你对话真好。
You bring such wealth of information,
您总是带来如此丰富的信息，
and I am really looking forward to talking to you
今天特别期待与你探讨
about the sixth energy center today.
第六能量中心的话题。
We would like to start with that question
我们想首先请教：
of the relationship between the sixth energy center and the autonomic nervous system,
第六能量中心 与自主神经系统的关联，
and what organs the center controls.
以及这能量中心掌管哪些器官？
As we have seen in the first part of this series,
如同本系列首部曲所探讨的，
the first five energy centers,
前五个能量中心
the way the energy center potentially looks after the plexuses,
透过神经丛的运作机制，
and through the plexuses
借由自主神经系统 的神经丛网络，
of the autonomic nervous system has influence over various organs
对体内各器官产生深远影响。
So today, we are going to talk about again,
今天我们将继续探讨
a very important, critical center.
这个极其重要 且关键的能量中心。
So this is the sixth energy center, the so-called Agnya chakra.
就是第六能量中心， 所谓的“额轮 (Agnya Chakra)”
A lot has been written about it in multiple spiritual treatises,
多部灵性著作都有 很多关于它的论述。
It is also referred to as the third eye in spirituality.
在灵性修行中， 它亦被称为“第三眼”。
The Agnya chakra, or the sixth energy center,
额轮，即第六能量中心，
is, as all of these energy centers go, very, very subtle.
如其他能量中心一般， 是极其精微的。
It is located at a midpoint, one might say,
它的大概位置可以说是——
if we draw a line from the center of the forehead to the back,
如果从前额中央向脑后划一直线，
and from the top of the ears,
再从双耳顶端划一横线，
where it crosses, at that intersection deep within our brain.
两线在大脑中的交汇处， 便是这个能量中心的所在。
The physical manifestation of this energy center,
这能量中心在物质层面的显化，
not the energy center itself, but the manifestation of this,
（并非指能量中心本身）
could be in the form of the optic chiasma.
可视作 “视交叉（optic chiasma）”结构。
What is optic chiasma?
什么是视交叉?
So, we have our eyes and the retina
我们的眼睛具有视网膜，
that is at the back of the eye, that is the back end.
位于眼球后部，
From the retina, you have nerves, and these nerves have their cell bodies.
视网膜上有神经， 这些神经有它们的细胞体。
The axons from these bodies form the nerves,
这些细胞体的轴突 汇聚成束，
which together make up the optic nerve.
形成“视神经 (optic nerve)”纤维。
The optic nerve is a collection of these axons, or these long tails.
视神经是这些轴突 或称长尾状结构的集合。
And the optic nerves from each, the left and the right eye,
左右两眼的视神经
they go back and they cross over.
会向后延伸并交叉汇聚，
That's called optic chiasma.
此结构即称为视交叉。
And they cross over and then they go and they terminate at the back of the brain,
交叉后的视神经纤维 最终抵达大脑后方的
in what is called the occipital cortex.
“枕叶视觉皮层 (occipital cortex)”。
So the impulses from the eye, the light that goes in
当光线通过瞳孔进入眼球 并在视网膜上引发化学反应，
through our pupils falls on the retina, creates a chemical reaction,
所产生的神经冲动
and that impulse travels back and through the various connections that it has,
会沿着视觉传导路径传递， 经过多层神经连接处理后，
it interprets vision, or what it is that we are seeing.
最终在大脑形成视觉感知， 让我们看见眼前的影像。
So the physical manifestation is considered to be the optic chiasma,
因此其物质载体被认为是视交叉，
but that's not the energy center.
但并非能量中心本身。
This energy center controls our eyes,
这能量中心控制着我们的眼睛、
our vision in terms of what it sees, what it interprets.
我们的视觉感知系统、 图像解析及视觉认知。
So that's the first part.
这是第一功能。
The second organ this energy center relates to is the master,
第六中心对应的第二个器官， 可谓是人体系统的“总指挥”，
or the conductor of the orchestra.
或者就像交响乐团的指挥家。
You see, like a big philharmonic orchestra,
试想一个大型的爱乐乐团，
there is a conductor - and that conductor is the hypothalamus.
总有一位指挥——而它就是 “下丘脑（hypothalamus）”。
The hypothalamus is a very small organ situated in the middle of our brain.
下丘脑是个非常微小的器官， 位于我们大脑的正中央。
And we'll talk more about it also in the context of the limbic system,
我们稍后会在“边缘系统”的背景下， 进一步讨论它的功能，
which is the seven so-called energy center complex.
此边缘系统就是所谓的 “七大能量中心复合体”。
But the hypothalamus is an organ that sits at the crossroads
然而，下丘脑正处 于人体两大系统的交汇点：
between the endocrine system and the nervous system.
内分泌系统与 神经系统的交界处。
So it secretes a number of hormones.
它能分泌多种荷尔蒙，
And these hormones in turn control other endocrine organs,
这些荷尔蒙又进一步调控 其他内分泌器官的运作，
such as the pituitary, such as the adrenal cortex,
包括脑下垂体、 肾上腺皮质，
such as the male and the female reproductive endocrine systems
以及男女两性的 生殖内分泌系统——
that give rise to the ovarian cycle or the spermatogenesis in males,
男性精子的生成、 女性卵巢的周期变化，
ovarian cycles in females.
都受其调控。
So the hypothalamus has four or five key functions.
总的来说，下丘脑 主要具有四到五项关键功能。
And the first one is to maintain the internal homeostasis
第一个功能在于维持 人体内在环境的恒定状态， (homeostasis)
by regulating the temperature and the basic biological functions
透过自主神经系统 调节体温与基本生理机能，
through the autonomic nervous system.
包括:
So that includes our blood pressure, that includes our thirst,
我们的血压数值、 口渴感受、
our hunger or our appetite.
饥饿感或食欲。
It controls our urges.
它同时掌管原始本能冲动，
It regulates our body temperature as well.
并调节体温的变化。
It has endocrine functions,
其内分泌功能方面，
and through the hormones it secretes,
透过分泌特定荷尔蒙，
it also controls the autonomic nervous system
它可间接调控 自主神经系统的运作。
via these secretions.
例如“肾上腺皮质（adrenal cortex）”
So say, for example, the adrenal cortex secretes cortisol,
分泌的荷尔蒙“皮质醇（cortisol）”，
and that is our stress hormone.
(那是我们的压力荷尔蒙)
So flight and fight reactions, for example,
它便主导“战斗或逃跑”的生理反应，
which is a very well-known response within human physiology,
在人类生理学中， 这是个非常著名的反应——
you see something that is a grave danger, you run away from it.
当你感知有致命威胁时， 你会逃离它。
Or if it is something you want to overcome, you fight it.
或者它是你想要克服的东西， 你会与它战斗。
So all of these are controlled through this hormonal system.
这整套应急机制 都是由荷尔蒙系统精密控制。
The hormonal system receives input -
这个荷尔蒙系统接收输入——
the hypothalamus gets signals from multiple nervous systems.
下丘脑从多个神经系统 接收信号。
This enables it
这使它能够
to control the functioning of the body.
整合调节全身机能运作。
And that hypothalamus is believed to be under the control of this sixth energy center.
而下丘脑被认为是受 第六能量中心所控制的。
So you can say that the sixth energy center practically is the lord and master
你可以说，第六能量中心 实际上是自主神经系统的
or mistress of the autonomic nervous system.
最高调控中枢。
So as part of this series, we have now reached a point
本系列节目至此，是时候
where we talk about the master control of this entire orchestra,
揭示人体这座“生物交响乐团” 的真正指挥——
and that is the hypothalamus.
下丘脑。
So that is another very important organ
它是对应此能量中心的
that this center refers to.
一个非常重要的器官。
The third organ that we would want to consider in this context
接下来要探讨的 第三个关联器官
is the pineal gland.
是“松果体 (pineal gland)”。
The pineal gland is a very, very small body that also sits very close to the hypothalamus.
松果体是位于下丘脑附近 一个非常微小的腺体，
And this pineal body secretes a hormone you're all familiar with,
这个微小腺体会分泌一种荷尔蒙，
it's called melatonin.
叫“褪黑激素 (melatonin)”。
And melatonin controls our sleep cycle.
而褪黑激素正是调控 我们睡眠周期的关键。
It's extremely important.
其重要性不言而喻——
Anyone who's crossed time zones knows jet lag -
任何经历过时差的人 必对“飞行时差”印象深刻，
the 24-hour sleep cycle controlled by melatonin.
正是由褪黑激素主导的 24小时睡眠周期（生理时钟）。
As the sun goes down, as the light goes down,
当夜幕降临，光线渐弱时，
melatonin secretion starts going up.
松果体便开始
And that is controlled by the pineal gland.
增加褪黑激素分泌。
So within that framework, if we go back to the Sahaj subtle system,
如果回到霎哈嘉瑜伽的 精微能量系统架构，
you have the left side, which is the so-called passive side,
人体左脉代表被动阴性能量，
you have the right side, the so-called active side
右脉象征主动阳性能量，
that we have in the subtle system within our body,
左右脉都在体内的精微系统中。
and then of course, the evolutionary side, which is the central channel.
而中脉则是 (灵性)进化的核心通道。
So you can see how there is a beautiful correlation between the function
由此可见， 下丘脑调节生理需求的机制
of the hypothalamus by regulating the body's requirements.
与能量系统存在着 精妙的对应关系：
In the morning, we feel hungry, at night, not so much after we have had the day,
晨起，我们的饥饿感明显， 入夜，我们的食欲就减退。
the whole body temperature actually starts falling down towards the evening,
体温实际上在傍晚时分 开始下降，
and it reaches its lowest temperature at night,
并在夜间降到最低点，
which is why we sleep better in the cooler environments.
正因为如此， 凉爽的环境更有助入睡。
If it's very hot, we can't sleep very well.
若天气很热， 我们就睡得不好。
And it is also believed that when the body temperature starts going down,
研究更发现， 体温下降的过程本身
it starts inducing the state that we call sleep,
就会诱发睡眠状态，
that we just lie down and go to sleep.
让我们躺下就能入睡。
Through this energy center, we can say that
透过第六个能量中心， 人体得以：
by monitoring our internal body through the autonomic nervous system,
经自主神经系统 监控内在环境；
by managing our sleep cycle,
调节睡眠觉醒周期；
it manages our both: passive behaviors such as sleep
平衡被动状态， 例如睡眠
but also the active side,
与管理主动状态， 例如日间活动
which happens during the daytime, when melatonin levels are very low.
（当褪黑激素处于非常低水平）。
So it is this magnificently managed control,
这是一套精密的调控机制，
extremely finely done by regulation of the nervous system
正是透过神经系统的调节
to these two or three organs that relate
与第六中心相关的三大器官 （下丘脑/松果体/视交叉）
to the sixth energy center.
的协同作用来完成。
As laymen we seldom get a chance to understand
作为普通人，我们鲜少有机会 深入理解或欣赏
or admire these complex communications,
人体内这些精密的通讯机制
rhythms and patterns that have been designed into us.
与节律系统。
This is really very, very wonderful information, Dr. Ashish.
阿希什医生， 这些知识确实令人惊叹！
We would like to know the evolutionary significance
请您谈谈这能量中心 在演化上的重要性，
and where the center is most likely located?
以及其确切位置？
So this center - hypothalamus - as you can imagine,
从演化角度来看， 下丘脑的出现
the regulation of the body of an organism was a requirement
是为了满足生物体 日益复杂的
from an evolutionary point of view,
调控需求——
it's putting maybe the cart before the horse
这也许有点本末倒置
or effect before the cause.
或因果倒置，
But even as we start looking at again, the aquatic life forms,
但即使我们观察水生生命形式
and then amphibians and early terrestrial, so on and so forth,
到两栖动物和早期的陆生动物等，
as the bodies became more complex, multicellular with more
随着身体变得更加复杂、多细胞化
and more defined organ systems, cardiovascular system,
并拥有更多完善的器官系统，
respiratory system, digestive system,
如心血管系统、呼吸系统、 消化系统等，
they needed a master control over that organism so as to survive.
为了生存，那个生物体 便需要一个“总控中心”。
If any of these systems are not well controlled, it can go out of whack,
若这些系统失去有效调控， 便会陷入紊乱状态，
and then that starts creating its own issues.
进而引发连锁性的生理失衡。
So which is why the hypothalamus is believed
就像大脑中的任何器官一样，
that hypothalamic nuclei, like any organ in the brain,
下丘脑结构中
is like anything else, it's just a group of cells.
有一群细胞， 称为下丘脑核团。
So anything in the brain is composed of cells that are called neurons.
大脑中的器官都是由 神经元的细胞组成的。
The hypothalamic neurons, maybe not the organ,
下丘脑的神经元， 不是其个器官本身，
but the neurons have been found in very primitive life forms as well.
曾被人发现存在于原始生物中.
So that is the evolutionary relevance of this particular energy center, if you will,
这正揭示了第六能量中心 在演化历程中的关键性——
as manifest through the existence of the anatomical organ,
从脊椎动物开始
which is manifest in vertebrates,
具象化为解剖学实体器官，
and particularly, of course, in the Homo sapiens as hypothalamus.
并在智人身上 发展为成熟的下丘脑结构。
So its evolutionary significance is profound,
因此，它具有深远的进化意义。
without the hypothalamus or a hypothalamic like body,
如果没有下丘脑 或类似的结构，
controlling the entirety of our vegetative functions,
调控所有自主生理功能 就变得很刻意、很困难。
which is why we don't have to think about how many times our heart has to beat,
正因如此，我们无需思考 如何调控
we don't have to think
我们的心跳节律、
what should be the force of the digestive propulsive forces?
消化道的蠕动强度、
How many times should we breathe?
呼吸频率、
What is the extent of breathing?
及呼吸深浅度等。
All of these functions, that is circulatory system,
所有这些功能， 即循环系统、
respiratory system or digestive system,
呼吸系统、 消化系统
and the thousands and thousands of processes in the body that are controlled,
及成千上万的身体运作
that needed that sort of system - you can think of it as,
都有这套精密的调控系统， 你可想象它为
as almost like a fly-by-wire technology that exists now in modern aircraft,
现代航太的“线传飞控”技术：
but the pilot doesn't really have to think,
飞行员其实无需思考，
just switches on as a master computer that takes over
主电脑自会即时维持 飞行高度、速度与航向——
and on a second to second, not even a minute to minute,
并且是以秒为单位， 不是以分钟为单位。
just as the aircraft maintains its altitude, its speed, its direction,
下丘脑正是以这种 “全自动巡航”模式，
that's exactly how the hypothalamus functions.
维持人体各项机能。
And that is its evolutionary significance.
而这正是其演化意义所在——
It has evolved to allow us to survive
这种演化机制让我们得以生存，
without having to put in a lot of cognitive effort,
却无需耗费大量心力，
conscious effort into our survival.
刻意维持生命机能。
So that's basically its evolutionary importance.
这就是它进化的重要性。
It is located
此能量中心约位于
just maybe below the optic chiasma that we spoke about.
先前讨论的视交叉下方，
And it is again, very difficult to maybe just pinpoint
再三强调， 很难精确地定位，
because it exists in the form of energy.
因为它以能量的形式存在。
We discussed that in one of the first episodes.
我们在先前几集中已探讨过，
So these don't exist in the state of matter,
这些能量中心 并非以物质状态存在，
but it's most likely situated, as we said,
但正如所述， 其位置很可能是：
you draw a straight line from the middle of her forehead,
当你从前额中央画条直线到后脑，
right at the back, and then from across from the top of her ears.
然后从双耳顶部画一条横线，
And where these two lines will intersect somewhere in the middle,
这两条线在头部中间的交汇处
just below the optic chiasma in that area
在视交叉下方
is where near the hypothalamus is probably where this energy center is located.
靠近下丘脑的地方， 就是这能量中心的所在。
I really like the analogies that you use to explain complex concepts,
我很喜欢您用比喻的方式 来解释复杂概念，
because if we do not have a lot of science background,
这让非科学背景的我们
it just gets so much easier for us to just understand that whole concept.
也能轻松理解 这些深奥理论。
That's very, very beautifully explained, doctor.
医生的解说确实精彩绝伦。
When we come to the functioning of the center,
现在请谈谈此中心的功能
how does it relate to the maintenance of balance
它如何维系人体的 整体平衡？
And is there, is this related to a direct control of actions, emotions,
这是否意味着此能量中心 能直接调控人类的行为与情绪，
the active passive aspects of human behavior?
包括主动与被动的 所有行为面向？
Absolutely.
绝对是。
So as we said, the neuroendocrine system is closely linked to —
正如前述，神经内分泌系统 与压力调节有着密切相关，
there's so much literature on stress and stress management
现在有大量关于压力的文献
and what causes stress and whether stress is even
探讨压力成因与管理机制，
a physiologically good thing to have because it is something called eustress,
甚至探讨“良性压力 (eustress)” 的生理效应，
distress, so on and so forth.
以及与“负面压力 (distress)” 的生理差异。
But when we look at the normal physiologic functioning of a human being,
但如果观察人体正常的生理运作，
it comprises a minute to minute or even a second to second awareness
其包含了分分秒秒 对自身与周遭环境
of our own selves as well as that of our surroundings.
持续不辍的觉知状态。
And it brings into focus our attention, our memories,
这种觉知整合了 注意力与记忆系统，
and we'll talk about this, of course, in the next episode as well.
我们将在下集深入探讨。
Our memories, attention, our awareness,
这种觉知涵盖了 记忆、注意力、自我意识、
our place within the universe around us,
我们在周遭环境中的位置、
whether it is our societies, whether it is our families,
我们在社会、家庭
whether it is our workplaces.
与职场中的定位。
And in this minute to minute, literally, existential sort of environment,
在这种分秒“存在性环境”中，
we react, we respond.
我们的反应、回应方式
And we respond in a way that is a very complex integral,
其实代表了个体 复杂的整合表现，
if you will, of who we are as individuals.
而我们每个人的独特性格
And who we are as individuals is again a function of our collective past,
是由多重因素所综合的： 我们的集体历史、
our individual past, our cultures, our ethnic identities,
我们的个人历史、文化特质、 族群认同、
our languages, our geographies, where we come from,
语言背景、地理渊源、 出生地、
the way we were raised, not everybody's raised the same.
成长经历。 每个人的成长经历都是独一无二的。
So whoever we are, this huge amalgam of our memories,
这一切记忆与制约的总和，
of our conditionings, all are governed by what constitutes the brain.
构成了大脑的运作基础。
And within the brain, it is this energy center that plays a particular role,
而在大脑中，第六能量中心 扮演了特殊的角色，
because it is also related to the notion of ego and superego.
它与“自我 (ego)”和 “超我 (superego)”有关联。
And we have these two institutions, there are other videos
我们有这两个机制——
that Sahaja Yoga gives us, that speak to it,
霎哈嘉瑜伽的影片有详细阐述，
but it gives you that sense of I-ness versus the others.
它们给予“我”与“他者” 的界线感知。
And that is where this energy center comes into play.
这正是第六能量中心 发挥关键作用的所在。
So in individuals who are well balanced,
在身心平衡的个体身上——
'balanced' is more of a metaphorical term
这里“平衡”更多是 灵性层面的比喻说法
or of a spiritual term, but individuals who do not react
或灵性词汇，
unnecessarily or excessively,
那些人都不会做出 不必要或过度反应。
if you see a cat and you start running in the opposite direction, that's a problem.
如果你看见猫就逃跑， 那便是问题。（过度反应）
If you see a tiger and you start running in the opposite direction, not a problem.
如果你看见虎才逃跑， 那不是问题。（适切反应）
Why?
为什么？
Because although they both belong to the cat family,
虽然它们都属于猫科动物，
those are two very different situations.
但那是两种非常不同的情境。
So that is where this center comes into play.
这正是第六能量中心 的调节功能体现。
And if there are individuals who react in a very different way,
在这种常态情境下， 有些人却表现出异常的反应，
in these kinds of situations, those are very generic situations,
这种情境都十分普遍。
But that is what defines a healthy state of this energy center versus not.
这往往揭示了第六能量中心 失衡与否的状态。
And therefore, it is very important to keep this energy center
维持该能量中心的健康平衡 是至关重要——
by developing through the Sahaj meditation process,
透过霎哈嘉静坐法， 我们能培育出一个
what we call a balanced, forgiving and a charitably disposed personality.
情绪平衡、具有宽恕能力 和乐善好施的人格。
Because that way, as you can now see the function of the hypothalamus,
由此可见， 当下丘脑功能正常运作时，
it does not have to secrete these hormones that will raise your blood pressure,
它就无需过度分泌 那些提升血压/心率的荷尔蒙，
that will raise your heart rate, that will allow you to react more aggressively
这些荷尔蒙会促使你 对“感知到”具有威胁性的环境
to an environment which you perceive to be aggressive,
产生过度攻击性反应——
which may not be aggressive, which may not be threatening to you.
即便该环境或许不存在真实威胁。
So life then becomes more a matter of perception rather than reality.
这样一来，生活变得更多 是一种“感知”而非现实。
And the calibration of one's response to that environment
而一个人如何“校准” 对环境的反应，
is what defines an individual from being relatively
正区分出他是否属于
what we call in conventional terms as reactive, immature,
传统上所谓的 “反应过度、不成熟”的个体，
to somebody who is, we say, more mature, sagacious.
还是所称的 “沉稳、睿智”的人格。
So think of a Lincoln or a Gandhi like personality
试想林肯或甘地的气度，
relative to somebody who is much more reactive or gets easily ruffled,
相较于那些 易受刺激、动辄失态的人。
we say, we just know some people who are just calm, more composed,
我们都认识前者这类人： 始终沉稳自若，
they don't react that negatively or excessively.
从不过度或负面地反应。
And that is where it kind of comes in, the importance of this center
这正是第六能量中心的 关键所在——
to maintain that balance within us, right action and right behavior.
它维系着内在平衡 与适切言行之间的微妙关系。
It does not mean we remain constantly passive.
这并不意味着 我们要恒常被动。
we remain constantly active.
也不意味着 我们要恒常主动。
Where is that fine balance?
我们要寻求 那个微妙的动态平衡点。
How do you calibrate back to that aircraft?
如同航机需要持续校正：
How do you maintain your speed, your altitude and your course
在情绪与灵性层面，
from a, shall we say, an emotional perspective
你如何校准， 以维持最佳速度、高度与航向？
or from a spiritual perspective is what this center is really about.
这正是第六能量中心 的核心所在。
And that's why it plays such a vital role in human spirituality.
这解释为何 它在人类灵性发展中 扮演如此重要的角色。
Thank you, Dr. Ashish, for bringing up that very wonderful point,
感谢阿希什医生 提出这个精彩观点，
a very relevant point about the level of reactions that we all may have.
关于我们反应程度的把控 确实发人深省。
And it is for each of us to, just look inside us, look around us
我们每个人都需要内省 并观察周遭，
to see where we find just giving reactions more than needed.
看看自己在哪里做出了 超乎必要的回应。
Like you explained with the example of the cat and the tiger responses
就如你提到的猫和老虎的例子，
to a similar situation or a different situation,
对类似情境或不同情境，
how they need to be.
我们应该如何反应。
But this is something that we are seeing a lot around us on social media
但在社交媒体和各种平台上，
and different platforms.
我们随处可见 过度反应的例子。
So, anything that you want to add to that
对于这点，你是否有什么要补充的吗？
just so that we can be more aware of our surroundings,
好让我们更能觉察到 周遭的环境，
our environments where we are?
我们身处的环境？
Fabulous. That's such a great point, Monika,
说得太好了。莫妮卡， 你提出的观点确实精辟。
if we think of our evolution,
当我们思考人类演化时，
but we don't have to go back to the aquatic stage.
其实无需追溯至水生阶段
Just about 100 years ago, just about 50 years ago,
不过百年前，甚至半世纪前，
there was no social media,
社交媒体尚未问世，
television and media did not play such a big role in our lives.
电视和媒体在我们的生活中 并未扮演如此重要的角色。
People had a much more quote-unquote pastoral lifestyle,
那时，人们过着所谓的 “田园式”生活——
certainly pre-industrial societies.
无论前工业化社会，
But even in post-industrial societies, it was not that much of a deal.
或后工业化初期皆然。
This influence of media and the environment around us,
虽然社区邻里互动仍在，
there were communities, there were neighbors,
但随着社交媒体崛起，
but with the advent of social media, particularly, life has become very reactive.
现代人的生活已变得过度“反应式”。
You are part of some kind of a social media platform,
你参与了某种社交媒体平台，
whichever it is, with your friends, with your office colleagues or neighbours,
无论你使用何种社交平台—— 无论是与亲友、同事或邻居互动，
as the case may be, you read a post about a topic,
当您阅读一篇帖文，
whether it is political, whether it is social, whether it is cultural,
无论是政治、社会或文化议题时，
and the brain processes it.
大脑便会启动处理机制。
Within our brain is a very important group
关键在于脑内的 一组神经传导物质，
of neurotransmitters - one of them is dopamine.
特别是“多巴胺(dopamine)”。
Dopamine is a pleasure giving molecule.
多巴胺是一种“快乐分子”， 能带来愉悦感和兴奋感。
Whenever we do or feel something pleasurable,
每当我们体验愉悦感受时，
there is a part of the brain called a substantia nigra that secretes dopamine.
脑部的“黑质 (substantia nigra)” 的神经核团便会启动分泌多巴胺。
Dopamine gives us that high, that rush.
多巴胺带来的愉悦感与兴奋感，
And where social media comes in, social media algorithms.
正是社交媒体“算法(algorithm)” 的运作核心。
I'm not a tech expert, but I saw a couple of documentaries,
虽然我不是科技专家， 但我看过几部纪录片，
and they explained beautifully that there is a full blown understanding
它们清楚阐明 人类神经系统的运作机制，
of the human nervous system, and particularly of how the dopamine
尤其是多巴胺如何
system works to produce that rush.
诱发这种兴奋状态。
So we are constantly through algorithms that are designed to generate that rush within us.
我们正陷于精心设计的算法之中 ——它们不断刺激我们 追求多巴胺带来的快感，
So we are constantly hooked onto it.
让我们对社交媒体产生成瘾。
We are given content or fed content that is based on these algorithms
我们接收的内容 皆由这些算法推送的，
that grab our attention and hold it.
它们掠取并牢牢抓住 我们的注意力。
And that is where this center is also where it's damaged the most,
而这正是第六能量中心 受损最严重之处——
because it keeps us on this endless loop.
因为社交媒体 让我们陷入无尽的循环之中。
We are essentially like animals that are on treadmills,
我们如同跑步机上的动物 不停奔跑，
that you're constantly fed that morphine of information, if you will,
被“信息吗啡”持续喂养，
and that triggers dopamine within us.
不断触发多巴胺分泌，
And that gives us that sense of high and that high keeps us hooked onto social media.
那种快感让我们对社交媒体 上瘾沉迷。
So the Agnya Chakra or the sixth energy center probably in the entirety of human civilization,
就额轮或第六能量中心而言， 纵观人类文明史，
recorded and unrecorded history, and this is not a hyperbole,
无论有无文字记载， （这并非夸大其词）
I genuinely feel it has never probably been more stressed due to social media.
我深切认为社交媒体 已为第六能量中心 带来前所未有的压力。
But what is the solution?
但有什么解决方案？
It's easy to identify a problem, but then what is the solution?
识别问题很容易， 解决方案是什么呢？
The solution is that through meditation,
解决方案是，透过冥想练习，
we can begin to stay away from that rush.
我们能逐步远离那种快感。
We don't need that rush.
我们不需要那种快感。
You don't need to constantly feel your presence on social media
你不需要时时刻刻感受 自己在社交媒体上的存在，
or see what is the latest post out there?
或紧盯最新动态——
Or if you posted something, has somebody read it or not?
或纠结有没有人看了你的帖文？
How many likes have you received?
你获得多少点赞？
Or have you not received it?
还是毫无回应？
So if you have not received anything, no responses,
若得不到任何回馈，
you kind of go down and then that dopamine rush goes down,
你的认可焦虑会导致多巴胺水平骤降，
you'll start feeling depressed.
进而引发你的低落情绪。
And we see this particularly in teenagers,
这现象在青少年群体尤为明显，
which is why the US Congress is acting very wisely.
因此美国国会已明智地
So to try to see if these social media platforms
开始监管社交平台，
can actually be modulated
试图调控这些社交媒体平台，
to avoid creating mental health issues
避免对敏感年龄层的族群 （例如青少年）
for susceptible age groups such as teenagers,
造成心理健康危机，
whose use can lead to extreme outcomes.
因为他们的使用 可能导致极端后果。
So yes, that's a phenomenal point that you raised.
您提出的观点确实发人深省。
And this energy center in particular plays a very critical role
第六中心确实扮演关键角色——
in either being susceptible and being influenced by social media.
决定了我们是否容易受 社交媒体影响的关键。
But then through meditative practice, such as the Sahaj meditation,
但透过霎哈嘉冥想的修习，
you can actually maintain a healthy boundary.
你其实能建立健康的心理边界。
So nobody's saying here, you should not interact with social media,
这里并非主张完全拒用社交媒体，
not use social media, social media is a way of life now.
它已是当代生活不可或缺的一部分，
We all have to live with it.
我们都必须与之共存，
The question is how and to what extent?
重点在于“使用方式” 与“使用程度”。
And I think with what you have shared, it seems like,
如您所言，这种冥想练习
with this meditation, not only an individual is going to benefit,
不仅能帮助个人培养
in the ability to self-regulate themselves,
自我调节能力，
it'll also impact the society at large.
更能将它辐射至整体社会：
Think about it like, if each of us just gets a little bit better
想象每个人如果都能改善反应模式时，
in terms of how we react,
这将提升整体社会
it's really going to impact the health of the society as well.
的心理健康水平。
Thank you, Dr. Ashish.
感谢阿希什医生
Thank you so much for this very wonderful information.
的精彩分享，
And we look forward to speaking to you again soon next time.
期待下次与您对话。
Thank you Monika, thanks for having me.
谢谢你，莫妮卡，很愉快的对谈。
Thank you.
谢谢。
We would encourage our audiences to follow
我们诚挚邀请观众跟随 霎哈嘉冥想创始人
the guided meditation video by the founder of this meditation,
希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维 的引导视频
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
进行冥想。
And do join us next time for yet another exciting conversation
也期待下次与阿希什·普拉丹博士
with Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
展开更多精彩对话。
Thank you.
感谢收看。
Shri Mataji: Today we are going to understand the center of Agnya,
希里·玛塔吉：今天我们将要认识额轮。
Agnya chakra which is placed on the crossing of the optic chiasma.
这个能量中心位于视交叉处，
The nerves that supply the eyes go backwards in the opposite direction,
供应给眼睛的神经 以相反方向往后延伸，
and wherever they cross, this subtle center is situated.
而在它们交叉的地方， 就坐落这个精微的能量中心。
It has a continuous connection with the other center
它通过“延髓 (medulla oblongata)”
through the medulla oblongata.
与其他脉轮持续连接，
This center has got two petals and this subtle center on one side
这个能量中心有两片花瓣， 而这个精微中心一方面
acts through the eyes and at the back of the head where you have some protrusion.
作用于双眼， 以及在头部后方那个突起的地方。
This is the physical side of the center.
这是这个中心的物质层面。
The people who talk of the third eye, this is the third eye.
那些谈论第三眼的人， 这便是第三眼。
Keep your eyes closed.
请闭上眼睛。
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
首先，请将你的右手 放在你的心脏上。
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
左手一直朝向我。
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
现在，在这里你必须在心中真诚地说： “母亲，我是否是灵？”
Ask the question three times in your heart.
在心中问这个问题三次。
This is a very fundamental question.
这是一个非常根本的问题。
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
现在把右手移到你腹部的左侧，
in the upper part.
在上方的位置。
Here press it.
在这里按住它。
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
这是你的导师中心， 你的指引，你的 Guru Tatva (导师原理)， 如他们所说。
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
请问一个问题， “母亲，我是否是自己的导师？”
This is the question to be asked three times.
这个问题要问三次。
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
现在将你的右手向下移到 腹部的下方。
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
这是完成所有神圣工作的能量中心，
all the pure work is done.
所有纯粹的工作都从这里完成。
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
所以要问六次， 因为这个中心有六片花瓣：
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
“母亲，请赐予我纯粹的知识。”
Six times you just ask.
就这样问六次。
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
由于这样的请求， 昆达里尼（Kundalini）开始被唤醒。
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
现在为了帮助昆达里尼上升， 你必须与祂合作。
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
所以请将你的右手放在左侧，
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
在你腹部的上部， 然后按在胃上。
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
在这里，为了帮助昆达里尼上升，
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
你必须充满信心地说： “母亲，我是自己的导师。”
This you have to say ten times.
这句话你要说十次。
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
这就是你要说的十诫，
that Mother, I am my own master.
“母亲，我是自己的导师。”
Now, ten times with full confidence.
满怀信心地说十次。
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
现在请将你的右手举到你的心脏。
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
在这里，你必须说， 再次满怀信心地说：
Mother, I am the Spirit.
“母亲，我就是那个灵（真我）。”
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
这是真理，你就是灵（真我）。
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
但你必须充满信心地说： “母亲，我是灵。”
This you have to say twelve times.
这句话你要说十二次。
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
你必须知道 全能的上帝是爱的海洋。
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
但最重要的是，祂是宽恕的海洋。
So He forgives.
所以祂会宽恕。
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
无论你做错什么，祂都会宽恕。
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
所以不要感到内疚， 把你的右手
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
放在左侧，在你脖子和肩膀 形成的角落处
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
现在在这里，你必须 再次满怀信心地说十六次：
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
“母亲，我没有罪疚感。”
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
请说：“母亲，我没有罪疚感。”
Sixteen times.
十六次。
I am not guilty at all.
“我完全没有罪疚感。”
Please say it.
请说这句话。
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
现在将你的手放在你的前额上， 这是一个非常重要的中心。
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
在这里，你必须发自内心地说： “母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Please say it from your heart.
请发自内心地说。
How many times is not the point.
说多少次不是重点。
Mother, I forgive everyone.
“母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
有些人会说， 宽恕是很困难的。
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
但这是一个迷思， 不论我们不宽恕或我们宽恕，
We do not do anything in both the cases.
在这两种情况下， 我们都没有做任何事。
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
但如果我们不宽恕， 我们就落入了错误的掌控中。
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
所以请诚心地说： “母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
现在请把你的手放在后脑勺， 同一个能量中心，在后脑部位，
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
让你的头靠在手上， 然后稍微向后推。
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
在这里，为了让你自己安心， 你必须说，
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
因为你总是感到内疚： “神圣的力量，如果我做错了任何事， ”
please forgive me.
“请宽恕我。”
Please forgive me, from your heart.
“请宽恕我。”发自你的内心去说。
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
现在请将你的手完全伸直， 把你的手掌心
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
放在头顶的囟门骨区域， 那里在你童年时是一块非常软的骨头。
Press it hard.
请用力按压它。
Press hard your scalp.
用力按压你的头皮。
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
现在你要转动它七次， 一边说这句话——这是你必须请求的：
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
“母亲，请赐予我自觉。” 因为我不能强迫你。
So you have to ask for it.
所以你必须请求它。
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
转动七次，用力按压， 并非常用力地转动七次。
Slowly saying that.
慢慢地说这句话。